Hi all good evening am I audible and visible guys okay thanks
so how's everyone doing
I'm trying to set up the screen guys give me a minute
Oh start screen sharing do let me know once you can see the screen
are you able to see the screen guys okay thank you so hey guys can anyone share
the whatsapp group link for Avril so guys how many of you complete last 11 questions
did anyone attempt it okay sure I'll do that I'll do that I'll do that
give me a second my screen share to act I'm switch Wi-Fi connection
guys give me a second I'll rejoin the call okay no not needed I believe like am I visible
and audible clear no just want to recheck with you guys and screen share is also working fine
right okay so we'll explore two properties guys margin collapse and red index and okay
these two properties okay right let's wait for another two minutes we scan even post in
whatsapp group we'll start in three minutes we're about to get started okay so there's
anyone having any other doubts no submit you'll be able to understand we are starting with
JavaScript so I don't think you missed anything but to watch the last class okay it's about
advanced CSS I hope you go back and try to get a hang of it okay so this is to Sambit Basant
submit drop me a github url you know then I'll check on that okay
let's create another folder in the classes which will stand for JS
right Sambit Tripathi and Sambit Basant both people I think you already greeted each other
in two classes earlier okay great I'll keep this open with me and we'll check this Sambit later
okay so github link is already shared wherever I'm pushing the code but I'll it's it's you know
pinned in whatsapp also you can refer from whatsapp group also but I'll reshare it
so this is the link guys okay and also in the whatsapp link I think time is also up we have
good amount of people so let's get started guys with today's class okay
so till now guys what we have covered in broader perspective right are two parts isn't it two parts
code code two parts I would say HTML and CSS we call this as a hyper text markup language
where it was just used to you know build the structure of layout right structure of our
website like what content to be showed and how it should be showed whereas this used for styling
the structure and we call this one as a cascading style sheet
right so I hope this two parts were clear to everyone right can you guys give me thumbs
up if you are clear with this two topics on broader level and the topics that we have
discussed till now cool so we are going to get start with the third I'm guys today which
is JavaScript so since this is a first class we'll move bit slow we'll understand best bit
history about what JavaScript is why it was built and how you know web development got you know got
this much of scope and how how this has been done okay so you know firstly if I go to do you
understand this keyword is web 1.2 web 2.2 or web 3.2 do you know this have you heard of this one
what are these are okay now let's see like what is web 1.0 firstly so not exactly versions but
these are like the how web development was progressed and how they have grown over the
years like if you see web 1.2 was simply built using HTML and CSS and they are only used to
build something called a static sites when I say static sites you don't have really like you know
behavior like you they don't have clicks or events that are being you the events you probably you
click it if you see a newspaper how that newspaper is like it's only one way right consuming you're
consuming the data but you cannot give data to that newspaper right it's just like you are trying
to read it so initially whenever websites were built firstly in web one point of face when like
.com boom was going on in 1990s so people used to only use websites for you know rendering data
like you can consume the data but you cannot actually play around with that all the other
things were done offline wherever you want to give a data it was offline is that point here like
when I say web 1.2 what do I mean it's just that wherever it's like a newspaper sort of things like
you have only you can consume that data like it's like reading a book online so that's how web
development started initially and this people know after that web 2.0 is somewhere like you
know the journey where people saw a problem that they want to do on automation and automation of
what of all the manual work you do like so now when I say only read only content but if you want
to give some data to it let's say you want to do an online banking or any other other sort of
banking how can you do it how can they do it so that's where you know they converted from like
art like manual efforts to automation and the first step towards doing this one or something
called us grow first internet have anyone heard this word grow first internet
even when I was going through right I don't know but I will show you what it was like okay
first websites were built then there was you know the websites were used to look like this one if
you see this image so Grover is someone like who built an internet protocol which can render you
render a menu like item and on click of them they can redirect you to the content which can
is only readable there are no forms or those sort of things but still the data is being shown only
not being consumed but this was like hyperlinks okay so that was a stack that came into the role
once they wanted to start automation like shipping more content onto the web is this clear on top
view what like the first invention was in terms of grow first internet this is something like where
they want to show menu sort of things if you see everywhere it would be like a hyperlink okay
nothing much deep in that but it's because it was just how used it used to work okay you can
explore on this if you want to read like what was a Grover and how it can be done but initial when
they got started the first protocol that was developed in terms of automation going moving
towards something called as web 2.0 was this one grow first internet then this one person
called Brendan H does anyone know this person name Brendan H have you heard this person name
okay this was a crazy guy who was also a CEO of Mozilla Firefox the team who actually went
on to build web development for us okay so this person has written whole programming language
case let me just show you his image okay this was a person who actually you know built the
JavaScript language but he was a co-founder of Mozilla project or Mozilla foundation whatever
you call Firefox is one of the product for them but he or someone who actually started
but when he did this one right this crazy person who wrote whole code in 10 days
what if I say you that JavaScript was built in 10 days and we are taking more than a month to
understand it it's funny isn't it so this person has coded the whole JS in 10 days and do you
believe like any person is so smart that one person can build full-fledged language in 10 days
do you think it's possible no right so this person when he built it now he firstly he they
used to call them call it as a live script okay live script okay because they wanted
this website to act like a life when they were going towards developing this web 2.0 like they
want more interactive so they call this has a script which will help you to interact making
the website live and when he built this life script now he made many mistakes many mistakes
while building it and those mistakes we famously call it as JavaScript features that will explore
one by one and even interviews I don't know why they expect us to know because those are the
pitfalls of JavaScript we'll explore them one by one but this language initially was built in 10
days that was a crazy thing that happened then you know the people from the back end like Java
they still mock front-end developers like hey you're writing a scripting language not a
programming language as such does anyone have heard this or face this one or like office life
or anything the world before frameworks like angular react people we used to use HTML CSS
JS and JS was actually not considered a programming language by the so-called back-end developers
because they say that this is just a scripting language nothing much more specific than that so
they've been like many things have been mocking with they have been mocking us but after the
frameworks came in after they got to know what are the challenge in challenges in it they're
acknowledging it slowly slowly but still back-end people are still back-end people okay but keeping
all the stuff aside now this as I said you when I say that this is not up to the mark
mark language like up to the mark into the market so there should be some organization right who
might be taking care of this life script who might be taking care of life script or building it so
that organization was called us ECMA have anyone heard this key word ECMA okay so these people
these are the group of people this is a group of people from different organizations they came in
they told like hey this is a really great feature this is a real great feature and this is a value
add thing that we if you want to move towards web 2.0 or do anything in the latest world right we
have to come together and build some really great features to it like are more rappers are adding
more things so they kept on you know releasing multiple features to this one okay multiple
features and one of the best features they released in which major amount of new changes
or new way of handling came in was ES6 which we call it as ECMA script version 6 like you say
anyone in the Java developer role they say that Java 8 is a more important thing because they
have introduced streams and functional programming in it isn't it because anyone applying for Java
roles they consider like Java 8 is mandatory I am able to relate with Java because I also
do work on Java right so in same in the same way ES6 is a one of the major releases that this
stream ECMA let's let me show you whose ECMA is like what they do on a brief okay this opened
in the new page I don't need this one let's say we open here okay so if you see this what this
is like stand you can see many things are there but if you see ECMA 6 this is a something where
they introduced too many things on JavaScript front okay they keep on building many things
that you need to you need help in but this is a team that who has built for us but let me see
yeah ECMA script 21
let me see ES6 document
okay this was a one of the website who made who actually handled it now they have released
too many good amount of things guys in JavaScript which made JavaScript a stable language or a more
of a better language now if you see a JavaScript is a JavaScript but if you see the most of the
things right whatever you see they are coming from the ECMA script now because people don't
really call ECMA script as a I mean like you have many names to this particular language that we are
going to learn but all those features again we say that it's HTML CSS and JavaScript that's how
people accepted it but something we are going we are using or we will be able to we'll be learning
something called as ECMA script because that's where you know many inventions came in and those
things will be keep keep on using it okay now in between I've talked about something called as
live script and ECMA script let's say this is an ECMA script but where does this name got converted
into JavaScript how does it got converted like when the decision was took so what happened is
right live script they gave it a name it was going good it was supporting features and everything
they didn't do anything but since at that moment of age this language was famous right this language
was famous so that they just use this Java and they added something like script to it that's why
these people keep mocking us hey you are writing a scripting language but you're not actually
coding it adding our name so this person itself Brendan H itself he is something converted and
built for us okay so if I show you even in documentation of JavaScript let's say if we
go for Wikipedia yeah this is a Wikipedia right so if you say designed by Brendan H of Netscape
initially others also have contributed to the ECMA script standard can you guys see this if I
have to zoom in okay first person like Brendan H was done it then ECMA script got introduced
okay then many things came in okay if I show you let's say if I search something called as
live script if it is there see in 1995 it was startingly called as live script then the name
was changed to JavaScript for the official release in December okay generally added to create
interactive websites that's how they have built it coming back to this one so this was a bit of
a history guys now this people this organization right we say that ES6 is a best version but they
kept on releasing many versions but we it got limited yeah yeah you can say that somewhere so
they kept on increasing multiple versions like ES version numbers kept on increasing releasing
but people stopped caring because now people have moved towards frameworks like angular react
or you can say view but what I feel like the world will come back to this one someday because
history repeats and things will fall back okay up to an extent you solve some problems you come
back and solve do better things okay but this was something how what was it like history about
JavaScript is that clear guys how JavaScript was created and why it was created I hope this was
just a theoretical thing we'll have much theory today and then we'll get started actual coding
okay then this is fine so this was created for adding interactivity or behavior to client or
you can say your HTML and CSS code but just think of it this is solving problem on a front end logic
isn't it but how come we are able to among this three guys among this three this one okay you
can search that Google you can search it which one is famous among them you will see that according
but this problem is if you see this this is solving front-end logic issues but what about
backend which is a more popular among three guys I didn't miss are you talking about this one let's
leave it this one as of now guys we will come back again pure.js okay but focus on this question
Abhinav will take it up in future okay focus on this question now like initially we use these
three things to solve the front-end issues now how backend you are able to build a backend servers
or backend applications because using js what was the innovation that took place here so because
if you see till now what we have learned from the history they were solving only to add problems
like to add a behavior and this end-edge created some issues so the one organization who took
responsibility of improving the language they kept on improving it okay but just think of it
like how we were able to solve the like this actual issue of backend does anyone have any
idea on this how we are able to code it in backend or how does murn and mean came into exist
and why we call JavaScript developers as full stack developers today node.js okay so I'll write
down here node.js but before going to node.js now tell me one something like if I'm considering
only front-end part even front-end part let's say you have HTML CSS and JS now where this
JS code is compiled and executed because we know this are both in browser where this is
executed and you know passed so give me thumbs up for the browser give me thumbs down for the server
okay I see equivalent okay guys both people are in a way right but I will tell you about
like actually what happened when I'm considering front-end part it is actually executed in browser
itself but now to understand any code or anything we need someone a machine to understand this one
right whatever we are writing logics JS logic do you agree with that if we are entering in the
browser and browser is not something being handled by one organization browsers are owned
by different organizations right do you guys agree with that it is this point that a different
browsers are there and different browsers are like owners are different organizations okay
nothing much uncle just now we are talking about history okay but can can you give me
a different browsers that you use in day life like what are the browsers important browsers
that you use in day life okay OPERA but do you use OPERA uncle in this day so I have Chrome
I have edge and one more guys brave duck duck go Safari let's say if I make this as a three
standard one right three standard one and three big giant companies are handling this one isn't
it and Mozilla let's say Mozilla Firefox we shouldn't miss that creators okay this has
four people handling who's handling Chrome who's handling Chrome guys who are building
this Chrome Google red I hope you know this and who's handling edge Microsoft
and who is handling Safari Apple and for this one Mozilla cooperation
these people also went on to build something called as brave okay now you know each of this
each of these people have built their own engines which will understand this code whatever
written in JS okay so one of the powerful machine which was introduced by Google was
something called as a V8 engine this was actually built on a chromium OS have you heard this
chromium OS okay so they built Google went on to build something called V8 engine now
Microsoft edges also built on something called as chromium US oh sorry OS so they also use some
same V8 engine to understand JavaScript and execute in their browser okay same in a same
way Apple has something some engine called as nitro which understand JavaScript and execute it
in their browsers and this people have something called as spider monkey who you know pass and
execute the code is this point here like we have HTML CSS by default that we are entering a tree
but to understand a program and execute and pass it we are seeing that it will be done in browser
and browser is not someone who builds language who owns it browser is something external products
like tools so each company have built their own respective engines or they took extra one like
support from the other OS's and build their browsers okay so these are the engines that they
have used to pass the code now this was all about front-end now people have told me to the
earlier problem which has like how where you were able to code it in backend now to write those
backend code also since in browser we were using one of these engines to understand code and pass
the code we need that sort of engine right which can understand code and write it down outside of
browser isn't it
so for that use case itself for that use case itself there's a one person called
have you heard person called ran Randall
have you heard this person's name
okay
interesting story guys if you go and read about him right he is a person who created node.js and
dino dino is something he also told like like same as a brendan edge he this person also
written node.js in you know very quick time he released it then if you see
on 27th may 2009 dial released this project called node.js runtime
okay then in 2018 after nine years he again created a new engine called dino which will again
execute that but what this person did if you understand about this one also this person also
right he was doing some phd in mathematics he left that mathematics degree and he went to
south africa to his hometown and then he went out to build something node.js now while he's
building what he did is like he don't want to write the whole engine code like whole javascript
parser code but what he took is like he took that same chrome engine because this was someone who
was giving better performance okay weird engine so he took help of weird engine and
then he added some more features to it he added some more features to it
and created something called as node.js this this product
by then once you had node.js you were able to write code
and execute it on a server because this one was giving us ability to create a server
okay i hope you can understand now that js can be executed both on browser
and non-browser environment
so one of the ways using any browser like chrome or anything for non-browser you have
to use something called as node.js is this clear from execution like
where you can use javascript and how does it work
nice so after this what happened is now because of this only we were able to create multiple
things like once you got the node.js you can write down the whole you can write down the whole
backend code in the node.js but in order to make node.js code also easy a something a new
framework which was built or something called as express.js this was specifically used to build
apis a robust framework that we'll be learning in future but i'm just giving you a brief of front
and back like when it comes to javascript ecosystem okay so express.js was created
to build your apis okay we'll come to apis also when we introduce it but till then
just consider this one i also explained apis in first class of our web development i hope you got
what i was trying to say here okay that's that's where a full stack got to birth okay where you
had on this client and both on server javascript can exist coexist and someone who is powering
here powering here is node.js and here different browsers
so that's the reason why i said that when you say that javascript can be executed both on browser
and server this is the reason why it can be done i hope this point is clear guys
okay now as you've seen that as you know that you know other than this one also javascript
has many applications if you see from the client perspective of one of the clients are like laptops
or desktop
and what else you have desktop laptop and ipads and everything but when it comes to this one we
when it comes to this one we were using same sort of you know
like programming language or same type of design but when it comes to mobile programming language
mobile apps you know we got too many people building too many things like flutter have you
heard of flutter right so this was again powered by google they built flutter they
powered flutter and they also you know many languages came for the mobile app development
okay now why does mobile app development is difficult guys just think of it why mobile
app development is compared comparatively difficult to hankit what does it mean can run a browser
so hankit just i've told you right javascript to execute javascript we have this particular
browsers and each browser have their own respective engines which can parse and execute the code
okay so that's what i was pointing to that it can run on browsers because they have
engines which can run the code whatever you write in javascript is that point clear
okay
so we can type the code on a chrome yeah yeah you can type the code on a chrome i can show that
i can show that okay you can type in any browser so to say okay now
yeah i'll show that i'll show that uh so for mobile apps uh let's complete this history then
we'll go for practical things okay the mobile apps the difficult thing was it was not running
in browser now when i say mobile app guys i'm not talking about something that you open chrome
right or any browser in mobile but i'm telling you like applications like you have a play store
app store or you say games that you have those are running on a mobile not inside the browser
environment right if you see we talked about till now in a browser and in a server level thing but
we didn't talk about os level right mobile os level like you have because here the os here the
os was windows or linux or you can say mac mac os right these three things but when it comes
to mobile you have something like android and ios right do you guys agree this like we have
a different os is working different ways but here we don't really meant to run the websites
in on to this os but we were running on the browser that was a fine issue we are still
not building apps on a desktop or the ipad but when it comes to app that have to run on this
like android or ios right we need some specifications for those reasons flutter type
of language were introduced which are compatible in building that but flutter is a different
language altogether but in when you learn javascript you also have an ability to build
mobile apps and that that comes with the react native have you heard this one react native
which is used to build native apps which are like mobile application specific like whatever your
apps you see swiggy zomato most of them are using react native itself to build it
so that again is based on javascript so javascript also gives you an ability to build websites
and also mobile apps or the applications that you see on mobile okay hope that is clear and
when it's come to you know applications from ai perspective or machine learning have you
heard of this keyword tensorflow tensorflow.js
or anyone heard is tensorflow
guys explore this one i'll give you tensorflow. in python it is famous but
okay this is a framework again which can help you to uh generally if you go for python
huh it is generally if you go by python right it is easy to write you know read the ml models
or build ml models right but if you if you even know the js you can still do it because
there's a support given by google who build the tensorflow.js i'm just showing you that
you learn one thing you will learn one good language which is javascript you will be able
to learn both clients and server side code you will be able to build mobile apps you will be
able to build ai ml projects also up to an extent is that point clear like why js is important
to learn or why we are learning this one i hope like i'm able to create that vibe that how that
is playing a major important role and why it is important all the things are built on this
language so if you whenever there are new enhancements are happening these are happening
on this one frameworks will come and go 10 years before there was no react
but 20 years before until today js is there js will be there in future also okay now
this is about 2.2 guys right when we talked about web 2.0 it was like more of a interactive
websites where user were interacting with the website isn't it now just think of it what's
happening in 3.0 just think of it what's happening in 3.2 guys
anyone like seen any 3.0 websites web 3.0 or like you know the idea or the intuition
towards web 3.0 is not yet matured okay not yet matured because whenever we say that
web right we are pointing towards client side client side logic like how you want to improve
client side like gpt uh uh uh that that was like for a back-end verse but if you see 3.0 is
something krishna mentioned something called as metaverse right you might have heard metaverse
you have seen this like uh apple's device where you wear those goggles and you are able to do
multiple events right multiple activities have you seen that launch oculus like oculus from meta
or like even apple had done it now in those in those advertisements they have seen yeah vision
pro if you remember vision pro uh they were interacting with websites using hands gestures
and even uh like you know i retinas and everything till now we had keyboard and mouses everything
but that was web web 3.0 that was one of the application google glass you can say
you can say this was one of the example or you can say in our uh you know in our language like
jarvis everyone knows jarvis right at least iron man jarvis something who listens to us and does
work so you can say that is what web 3.0 is talking about now from web 3.0 also we don't really know
the applications or how long it will be developed or what we are trying to achieve it since for web
2.0 it was a clear constraint that hey we want to add interactivity and that was clear but for
3.0 there's a metaverse then there is something like cryptocurrency uh but we don't exactly know
what how the future is going to be okay the subject is not yet perfect like the intuition
that you want to do but there are many applications are coming where it is giving you to you know
uh ownership of it like have you seen many things which were based on this one
uh blockchain based technology where you can own stickers and other things and you can go into a
dream land and buy the lines and play around with those
nfts yeah nfts i hope you have heard of nfts okay so now what does nfts idea was like in 2.0 till
1.0 you're consuming data and in this you are interacting and you are sharing the data
then in 3.0 this people gave an idea that hey we are talking about ownership of a places or
ownership of that idea okay so if i talk about three perspectives that are innovating this one
or creating each one have their own way of explaining things right so this is what happening
i believe still web 3.0 will also take advantage of js and will build up on it
because interfaces are built that way okay yeah yeah creating a virtual world that's what
actually i was talking about using nfts they used to say right it just two projects are again
interlinked cryptogenesis nft but i i hope the basic idea is clear uh what i was talking about
3.0 right
so this is just an introduction guys that i was talking about like how and why javascript is
important how the uh like how how this all came into an existence how this is happening in what
can be the future version and thing right so i hope you enjoyed it this is just a like a talk
that we had but now we'll go and see how we can do this and how we can use javascript excited guys
for javascript
is going to be a very good journey i hope uh i we travel together and learn too much so for the
people who wanted me to write javascript in browser i go to console guys if you see here
i just do two plus two and i'm able to do arithmetic operation okay i can run a for loop
i'm just showing this that you can do it and i'm writing in a browser in a chrome browser
okay i'm able to print it this is fine uncut i think you were asking it right how we can code it
okay why did you learn python then every every application has in own importance but
you know uh you should you should get to know it like where you are applying those tools or when
how that's why we say that javascript is like having a vast amount of applications where if
you learn one thing you're getting too many things and it's like buy one get many things
and it's like buy one get many things okay this is a shop where you buy learn one thing and get
many opportunities around okay so till now guys let's create one folder uh javascript and what
is the last class that we ended seventh class so i'll create a class eight here
now inside class eight let's create one simple index dot html file now this is something that
we already know okay what this file is talking about let's render something like h1
okay let's say heading and if we want to give a style we also know that if we if we want to link
it we can link using style sheets isn't it let's build up one style sheet style dot css okay
isn't it let's build up one style sheet style dot css okay
all right let's make some color to it h1
color
okay random this is what we know till now isn't it this is what we have learned now let's let's
do something and let's add another file here when you go to the html file okay what i'll do it here
is that i'll create another now if you see i have used something called as link but if i want to
write a javascript right anytime in javascript in html or i want to link of javascript file here
i can write it anywhere let's say i can write a script tag script tag if i write down two plus two
okay i can do anywhere like if i write down anywhere it it should be it would be executing it
in body in head or anywhere okay
oh
you won't be able to see in the browser though let me do one thing i can do something like
console dot log console dot log guys is equal to the print statement that you learn in a
different language it can be system dot print dot ln or anything that you see okay now what
i'm just i'll do is like i'll open this in the browser since visual studio code doesn't have
an ability to run javascript but browser does it does have it right let's open with live server
okay now if you see open inspect tool and if you see the 444 got printed three times
and that's coming because if you go and open this file index dot html
yeah for js javascript if you want to print anything you use console dot log
because you are trying to print something in the console
okay that's how it works that's how you remember how the print statement works in js
is that point clear guys that i can add a script file anywhere that i want to
anywhere that i want to
okay i hope this logic is clear it will work in anywhere
but what's the standard practice right what is the standard practice that i can do
okay i'll comment this one one of the standard way of it's like uh there's nothing like standard
all people write all outside of codes but like we have i've just shown you like how can you write
js here inside the html and how can you add a create a new file let's say i have something called
this uh index dot js file here let's say you write console log here again uh and we do uh
you know this one a statement whenever you learn any programming language let's start with it
okay now if you want to link that file if you want to link that file anytime what you can do
is is inside the script tag you can always add a source what is the source of this particular script
or what how what where is the code for this script tag you can give this way once you give this again
i'm going inside the here uh and i'm refreshing it okay if you see this particular file was linked
and this was the line added now if you see whenever i'm refreshing it uh this line will
be executed let's say if i click apply here hello world was printed so that's how you connect three
files it can be your html it can be css and it can be gs is this clear how do you link those files
and how can you add a javascript in the same file this is just an introduction i haven't taught you
any new topic it's just like how can you use the javascript in the html along with that
guys no doubt till now right no doubts until now right
okay i hope there are no doubts now now there is something new that i want to show
it's like okay till now okay you've shown me in browser what what's a use where how can i do it
in node.js you told about node.js that can be uh allowed you can use it to you know code it in the
backend way and how can you build a server around that for that one right you have to
install something called as node.js go to this website guys uh and you know go for something
called as lts long time support which is recommended for most of the users if i give you this site
uh take this and download it how many of you already have it or how many of you don't have
it guys give me thumbs down if you don't have this one download it okay please go on click this one
okay go and click this one lts one it will be automatically downloaded okay and you have to
install it guys i'll wait for a minute or two once you install it
okay once you like let's say you click a download i'll show you once you click a download this will
be done uh it's taking a good amount of time 70 mb if your internet speed is good uh you'll be
able to download it fast so i'm just showing how can you do that
custom setup uh yeah i'll just show you like once you click this right uh for i can show
for the mac guys because i have this macbook right or else i can share you a recording where
how we can install the node.js okay you can continue it
you can continue it and you can agree uh you know disagree with the like agree with the license
and go ahead and install it okay
guys would you be able to install it if i give you one recording or you can search in the youtube
for the node.js installation part can i go ahead with the topic
can i go ahead with the topic
okay cool thank you guys now what i'll do it is like i'll open a terminal here let's say in the
class 8 i create open a terminal since you want to run a server or anything once you are installed
node.js right once you are installed the node.js you can verify what is the node version you are
having let's check my my version okay uh let's say it's hyphen hyphen version if you see i have
something a version called 18.8 but the latest version is 20.2 whatever version you are having
that's okay or greater than 14 is something you needed okay i print this one once you check the
version and if your node.js is available now let's see what i'll do i have this file index.js
now i'm not executing in the chrome but i'm executing in this terminal i'm just saying that
hey node can you execute this file of javascript and i'm clicking enter now if you see hello world
got printed even what i can do i can do something like console.log uh let's say two plus two basic
example uh again i execute this one now if you see two things i have it output it is that clear
like you can run javascript in both browser you can link with html you can also run individually
js files using node.js so i hope i have justified this part like how can you use them now
yes if this thing is clear uh we are ready to get started and deep dive inside the language part
okay so uh what i'll create uh you know folder here is that
let's have a folder called variables
and data types
okay let's say i have something called as variables.js okay
so guys can you give me your own definitions of understanding variables
what do you exactly understand by variables how do you uh pursue this keyword variable
how do you uh pursue this keyword variable
since you have studied some sort of language if you haven't studied that's fine but
just think of what you understand by word variable
guys no one
just use it to store data identifiers okay can store value can store data okay uh let's say
let's say i'll tell you this one um i want to store milk what sort of vessel you will get it
in the home what type of vessel you will get utensil you can say
okay uh which is having a bottle sort of things right or a patella wherever you can pour milk in
right right so each and every other item uh have a particular thing which can take that item and
put it in that right you have boxes you have almaras where you can put the items in it or
you can have complex boxes where you put your pencils in it you have mobile where you store data
or contact list same way in programming language if you want to store data right you want to store
data variables are somewhere are like a containers that can store the data this is definition good
enough guys to remember it like these are the containers just containers which can take the
value okay let's say
variables are containers
that can store different values or items because container can be anything a bottle or any type
of vessel that you see or utensils in your home it can every utensil is used for you know different
types of storing right same way variables also have different use cases okay now so one of the
way one of the way that you can store and declare a variable now when i say declare a variable
it means that i'm naming a variable okay uh if i tell you in a specific way how we can say that
is that uh this is milk bottle or or you say that that way whenever you say that this is a
particular items container then you name that particular container right cooker is for rice
or they say something that way so you have to name so you never you are doing it you declare it
let's say one of the way to declare it is like where a or you you say in different languages
int a like in chava or you can say in different things right now if i'm saying that this line
right when i'm saying this line what is this i'm saying that a is a variable and this variable
name is a container name is a and this container will have value 10 in it this is good enough
explanation guys are you able to understand where i equal to 10 what do i exactly mean by that
okay now where is a old way old style of writing
or declaring variables and this was again given by it itself who created in 20s okay
itchway let's say itchway okay now why i'll tell you this one why this is not good enough i'll
tell you let's say i open an integrated terminal and i clear this one i say node variables
let's say dot j's if i execute let's say okay i okay let's say ls i have this file
okay nice made a spelling mistakes this uh keep a eye on you know this one and keep making mistakes
on spelling mistakes okay okay i didn't anything printed here so it doesn't didn't work let's say
i do this one you see this 10 is getting printed here that's fine so let's say i do this one
where is equivalent to end no i'll come to the address t give me a second okay i'll come to that
now let's say again i use where a equal to let's say i store your name this day here
do you think this is a right way of writing a code
okay
the reason guys any reason i see eight people giving me thumbs down what could be the
why are you giving me thumbs down i just want to understand okay yeah i'm re declaring and
initializing that same variable right so now two keywords i got declaring and initializing
okay get out i wish it will remove an inside listing okay now great but
what's happening here is that let's say i have told this is a milk bottle
and inside that i'm storing a floor is it good
all right not a right way of doing it so firstly coming back to this definition of declaring and
initializing so this when i'm what do i mean by exactly declaring is that i declared this
variable as a i'm named it as a it's like giving a name like you name a person or you name anything
like declaring it but what position or what they'll contain is something like initializing it
initializing it means that what you'll put in that container okay that that definition
is clear right declaring and initializing
okay
declaring and initializing is clear guys okay now we say that this is a wrong way of writing a code
okay but now let's understand what's happening in js if i click enter
okay 10 is printed that's fine i go and print it again a
okay now do you see this it's printing 10 and it's also printing rusty
so what we thought by default is like hey you cannot re declare that same thing you cannot
give the name same name to that particular thing right but it is a we are able to do that
this was a one of the mistake that i created okay that hey i'm able to that's okay that if i want
to store in a if i want to store a dristy i can update it let's say variable can take if it is
taking let's say 10 liters of milk if it is having more space it can supposedly take 12 liters of milk
that's fine but how can i rename that same variable right it's not it shouldn't be allowed to do that
isn't it do you guys agree with that
so the problem that i'm trying to point out is
re declaring of same variable
are you able to notice that in python it allowed okay then python
guys i'm not sure about python but in i'm talking about some you know fixes that has been introduced
now i'll talk about them but here what's happening is like firstly in this example guys
let's leave python aside for this when you're whenever you're learning new language right
learn it from fresh understand it like what is user's perspective it would be easy for you that
to name one person and put that container item in it or like you can put any like you can always
declare again and again it creates uh too many mistakes and too many problems of understanding
and debugging is also important or difficult but coming back to this example guys i've just
declared two variables and reinitialize them so using where i can re declare and also i can
reinitialize right okay is this point clear guys that i'm able to redeclare and initialize using where
okay now in es6 right in es6 in es6 which is our 2015 version what happened is they introduced
two ways of declaring a variable let and const okay let and const two types of variable now let's say
if i say that let a equal to 10 again i said let a equal to i give any name let's say i give it
uncle do you see this it is highlighting both the a's and it is giving me a mistake destroying
is this dot js file is throwing mistake now it says that cannot re declare a block scope variable
now it says that cannot re declare a block scope variable a leave block scope and everything for
now yeah it's a let and const were introduced in esx uh some bit but what i'm trying to point out
here is that whenever i use these variables they say that you cannot re declare a like variable
is this point clear when you use this let what what if i remove this let what if i just remove
this let it is allowing me to store anything but it is allowing me to reinitialize it is allowing
me to reinitialize that variable so let's write down this point let allows to reinitialize a variable
variable
whereas it doesn't allow to
re-declare it
okay
now now let's go and see what const talks about it says a const i'll say b equal to 10
now again if i go and const b equal to 20 again it says that same issue right firstly it doesn't
allow to re-declare that same variable first point again even if i try to reinitialize that same
variable let's say it is showing here it is not throwing us any error but what if i do and print
it let's say if i go and try to run this file and print it now it says that assignment to constant
now it says that assignment to constant assignment to constant variable okay
when i say constant it is meant fixed final value you cannot reinitialize also
okay is this point clear like what const does
const doesn't allow to reinitialize or re-declare a variable
okay is that point clear guys how where let and const behave how these three things behave
yes anyone having any doubts these are basic things but
i hope you will be remembering this one
okay let's let's draw the chart for this one okay so that you remember
so
let's say if i say that re-declaration
and re-initialization
okay let's say i have where let and const
yes help me out can i re-declare a where can i re-declare a where guys
yes can i reinitialize the where
okay yes can i re-declare let
yes can i reinitialize let
yes let no right can i reinitialize let
okay let reinitialization yes right for const
both the things no right great thank you guys i hope this point is clear for you that how
these things are playing around so now understanding this point which both variables
feels like are actually should be used
when you are declaring any variable what would come to your mind which thing should be used
do you think where would be a great right idea to use anytime
okay right so in industry right in industry if you are using this variable in today's life
this will be flagged to be fixed
let's say i write down not to be used
even if i'm using anywhere while coding it you'll flag me out
okay i'll come to that someday okay whereas whereas let and const when you would go for let
when you would go for const
when you would go for let and when you would go for const
whenever you want to declare a final variable final or static which doesn't change over the
time go for a const which i think will change over time
which needs to be
changed
okay so i hope these two things are clear like use let and const and i hope the basic difference
between them is also clear now guys here there's a one more thing that i want to show you guys is
that do you see here i'm also able to put our numbers and strings into the same containers
like i didn't say that this is an integer or this is a string or this is something right
like if you go for java they strictly you like typed on int long string char right all of them
but here we don't have them so the reason is that javascript is loosely typed language
and dynamically typed when i say dynamically let's say there are three keywords guys they used it
weekly loosely
dynamically
okay
okay these three words are used when they why they use these two keywords are they go with synonyms
because you don't need to
you don't need to
say which type of container
there's a step of container now when i say type
is data type right what is the type of data that you want to store okay that you don't need to
okay that you don't need to say to js it will understand it runtime dynamically
is this point here why we say these three things
for javascript is loosely weekly typed and at runtime dynamically it will understand
what type of data type it is till then it won't flag you like you can store anything using
latent cost that point is clear now okay now now coming back to this something called as data types
let's move to the data types
so
okay on top level right on top level on top level what all the data types that you know
the scheme with those guys names that you know firstly how many types of data types what are
the categories of data types that you know you go you if you have learned any language
every language have two types of data types firstly can you give me those categories
there is that i understand it but how do you categorize data types
uh no
think of it do you remember this keyword something called as primitive
and non-primitive
right i hope you remember this case both things are data types only
right now what all things that you can think of like what will come in primitive
primitive
as you many member told earlier like int car floats here for most of the things i'll tell
you two things guys number is a data type which can store int and float and double
and long to say so okay from for the people who are coming from jar background number is a
keyword which like number is a data type which will store everything is that clear
now then there is something called as string
this will store both string and care what is the different between care and string guys
guys i'm writing this now not to confuse you but this is for the people who are coming from
different language background if they are able to understand if you are completely beginner
no issues number is a place where you store you can know you can store any number and string is
a place where you can store any string like string and i say string it's a group of characters
alphabets okay
what's the different between okay i've already told you car is a single character
single letters you can say a string is a group of characters okay then what would be the third
type guys commonly you think boolean right right which stores true or false
then here the in primitive they also introduce something called as null which doesn't mean
like whenever you have to give any empty value like just you can introduce null
empty is something called as null okay i hope this point is clear
okay on top level guys on top level these are the type of data that you would generally deal
with isn't it strings numbers booleans and null
i see one thumbs down right there are other few parameters too but i don't think that you would
be using it in day-to-day life if i go for standards give me a minute
okay
so there's one more thing guys that i want to talk about is something called as
big num big int okay big int again used for larger numbers okay that but not needed here the
range of number is too high okay not like java or any other language the range of this particular
data is too high and the funny thing about java script is that you don't need to declare type of
that you don't need to declare a type of data type right you don't need to say that it should
be a long or it should be anything by default it will get it okay but on top level these are
the four things which are in the primitive and when it comes to non-primitive what are things
that you generally see
arrays
and this
no don't need it not needed somewhere typecasting anything map okay
classes objects
here instead of classes java script is mostly preferred as a functional programming language
serial so you can say functions instead of classes we'll talk about classes use case of classes in
javascript how they come how they are working but we'll say functions okay these are the top
broader level category guys like how this primitive and non-primitive works but let's
explore them one by one it will take hardly 10 minutes i guess all you you already know this one
but i'll just take 10 minutes of this one to just clear uh re-explain and close it up okay
so let's say i have i'll start with numbers firstly
so what all things you can store let's say const a equal to 10
so what all things you can store let's say const a equal to 10 also you can store const a equal
b equal to let's say minus 10 a negative and positive okay then you can also store const c
equal to let's say 10.345 something like in a decimal unit again i can also store
minus 10.345 all the four things i can store let's say i show you console logging all of them okay
let me see clear ls node so whenever you are typing it you have to execute those file names
execute those file names data types dot j's now if you say i'm able to execute all of them
right this is a one special operator guys one special operator if you want to know
what is a data type of any particular thing then you have to use something called as type
of whenever you give something called as type of that particular you know it will give what
type of data type it is let's say if i re-execute this file do you see this it's suggesting it's a
number this is clear what this keyword is type of i will keep on introducing new things so that
you get used to it okay now numbers are done let's go for something called as strings
okay i'll do const e i'll store single character q okay
const f let's say i store hello or whatever suggesting okay i can print both of the things
i'll also print let's say type of e and also i'll print both the things okay
okay now if you see when i'm typing type of e it is giving me as a string for both like though it
is a single character and here the funny thing is single quotation or double quotation doesn't
matter everything is considered string okay in javascript whatever you give okay i hope that
point is also clear like string data type and number data type now
next thing is something like i was talking about something called as null right
g let's say if i print gif null and i also do console log of console log of type of g and let's
say i also do print g okay so you can use commas in console log which will print all the types okay
you see type of g it says as an object because a null by default it's an empty thing
till you don't assign a value it will show that way type of g
uh this one i'll tell you why we got is an object i'll get because uh you know most of the languages
which have been oriented such an object oriented programming right behind the scene everything is
considered object isn't it if you are bit experienced with any programming language
but i'll explain in javascript terms when we go for uh the concepts actual concept but remember
this like when i type when i check the type of a null value i'm getting an object and value as
a null itself but we'll pick it up in the future okay why object data type is coming as like this
one like object okay then uh bullions right let's say h true uh
okay
now if i print this now if you see i'm able to print two true false and type is becoming
bullion so these are the broad level categories guys what you generally see okay
uh right let me write down bullion but i want to show you one thing here is
there's something called undefined in javascript does anyone have uh
yeah i was coming to that something right away
okay now two things says one we need to understand undefined and not defined but before going to this
one i hope these examples are clear right i was using const everywhere because i was initializing
and reusing the same thing but if all this all these things are clear can anyone explain
what do you exactly understand by these two things
let's say i print something like console log of alpha
what i am supposed to get as a value output do you see do you see anywhere we have a declared alpha
variable no right now when you haven't declared it what you are supposed to get
if you haven't declared we have not declared it
is it's in the word itself like we haven't declared it we
not defined it we have not defined it right so that's what error upendra like if you see this
what sort of error you will get it says that alpha is not defined
so
is undefined is clear what undefined talks about
sorry not defined not defined not defined talks about variable
which is not declared
it okay clear guys now i'll do something like
if you say till i we have declared i'll declare something like j let's say j and
do something like console dot log of j
okay and i try to print it now okay let's say i'll clear this console using clear i'll comment
this line because this will throw error and stop the execution that's how i print this
do you see this i'm getting undefined
so what undefined talks about is
when variable is declared but not initialized is that clear two steps guys firstly not defined
goes for simple thing like if you haven't declared anything if you want me to use type
of i can do that also type of let's say what we'll get here in the type of okay parallel
let's say also i print the j and for not defined you'll you'll be thrown some error but here
let's execute this one and see this you see this type of is also undefined because runtime
you don't know what type it is now is this definition clear
i'll explain undefined keyword in further depth in further depth in the next class when we declare
when we understand one more concept called harvesting we'll come to that but i hope
primitive data types is clear guys whatever things we have discussed or you hope those
topics are clear now we'll go to something called as reference data types are non-primitive data
types let's say non-primitive first one as you suggested let's go for arrays what is an array
according to you
what is an array
give it don't try to get a bookish definition just say collection of same data type or collection
of items all right collection of items let's say collection of items now but here the only
difference in javascript is that we don't care about type of items we can store any item
it's like a person like a foodie like keep on serving i'll eat everything
that's how arrays are in js like they can take and consume anything let's say if i define after j
uh let's say okay now inside this one thing surely you can declare same data type
or else you can say that i'll have string let's say my anyone's name some bit okay then i say
one then i say two then i can say true then i can say null so i stored all the values okay
now let's say console dot log of
type of k and print k similarly console dot log of type of l and print l okay clear this console
print it you see this here type of kl is coming as an object
object because we came for the non-primitive data types by default
in non-primitive data types everything is as an object
okay in primitives you will have different data types but when it comes to non-primitive
everything is an object arrays whatever you are storing inside is an object object can be of any
type it can it doesn't need to be a same type of data that you are putting it here it's a collection
of items everything that whatever you can you want to put it you can declare in that
is that clear guys arrays in javascript collections of values
which can store different data type values okay yes anyone having any doubt till now
right now comes actual main powerful concept guys objects in js
now whenever you go for any object oriented programming or anything right whenever you think
of objects right abhinav will take in 10 minutes will take the in break in 10 minutes then
five minutes i'll complete the object and functions then we can take it five minutes on works
works
okay guys just cooperate with me for some time we can end the class soon if it's up to you but
let's see whenever you think of objects in any language what do you see it what do you
get an idea of what are you storing in objects
okay think of it guys whenever you are thinking in terms of object what type of data you are
storing let's say you are building a class why are you building a class
anyone coming from object oriented programming why this class works data of a group or
let's say can i say this as a custom data type
okay because whenever i say class like whenever i say create a class of a building i'm storing
a building as a data type and so i'll declare multiple things isn't it so objects are generally
used to build your custom data types where which can store any data that you want okay
let's say how can you declare an object here let's say isaac const object whenever you're
declaring an object you can create open a brace and let's say instead of object let's say we're
creating some kind of person object a person will have first name let's say some bit
last name will have
uh we have three party and under some bit so i'll be using some let's say i'll use my back
and last name shatma okay and let's say he'll have also a phone number
right let's say i give some random number okay and also he'll have h
okay let's say 20 okay so this is what a custom data type looks like right like if you go for
someone coming from a background of java he would have built a class like this one
and he would initialize or else he would say this way right guys pardon me if i'm writing this
but this is how it looked like right last name then you declare all the things
and you build up because you can create instances and you can use it right but the idea is here is
that you building a custom data type there is no data type declared in this language which can help
you to store this content so we created a data type called person and in that we are storing all
these details is this clear now one way of accessing this items right let's say i'll show
accessing a object later but how can you declare and console log it
and now if i do something like type of let's say type of okay and i print it if you see i'm
still getting an object and it is printing this one okay clear guys about uh like objects
so now we'll take break and we'll come back uh so that i can get your full energy
uh how many minutes break you need okay uh let's say if you want that type of first name right
okay
you see the string is being printed because it's a type of string
some bit uh guys how many minutes break you need it please put it in the chat uh
because i would need uh can we use let instead of course yeah you can surely use
you can surely use
but if what why i'm putting this constant right i'm not trying to update this one
uh guys do you need a break or should i continue because i've received mixed uh you know uh
reactions if you need a break give me thumbs up
okay many people are needing it uh guys let's take some break and let's come back and because
i would need uh 20 25 minutes or more like to close the class uh let's say i give you
eight minutes break okay let's meet back in ten by eight minutes guys
thank you
you
guys is everyone back
i see three people four
four cool five great guys thank you thank you so now till now everything is clear right
arrays objects and primitive data types everything we have one thing left which is called as functions
now what do you think function is all about what do you think function does
or when we use uh methods or functions what is the use case of functions when do we actually need a function
like any random definition that comes to you on the top of the mind
type it that down type type that inside a block of code that can reuse okay uh anything else guys
shoshanga suggested a definition a block of code that can be used
there's any other definitions which performs a task
okay i got two definitions a block of code reusable code right great so can i say this way
okay create a function when you want to perform a specific
task again and again
can i say this a function definition like it's a that function is doing a task for us
but when we want that thing to do it again and again we can create those functions
and the definition how do you declare it in javascript is something you use a function
keyword once you use a function keyword now you have to give a name to that function
uh krishna you have raised hand okay you have lowered your hand again
okay oh once you give this keyword function then you have to give the phone like let's say
coffee machine is a function now after that you give this braces then you have this something
called this one now inside this braces let's say inside this braces whatever values you give
are comma separated and those values are called as parameters or specifically function parameters
okay and whatever you are writing between these braces right
is called as
function body
is this point clear guys
uh props the arun will come to that when when you can say props and why we say props
will come to that use case but future but whenever you are talking about a js function
generally whatever you are passing inside this one is called as functional parameters
and whatever you write a logic inside this is called like let's say a function body no
i'll return a simple string guys i'll return a simple string i'll talk about the syntax the way
i am writing a string where i am i trying to you know write a dynamic string i'll talk about it
i need let's say this is something like i'm trying to say quantity
how much quantity of coffee i need and i say that also type of coffee or let's say drink
okay and i can do something it's like i can receive quantity here and also drink
okay this is a function that i declared it
now if i want to call if i want to execute this function or let's say what we say
in order to execute this function you have to suppose to call this coffee machine
i mean you're going to a coffee machine and saying that hey i need uh 200 ml of coffee
let's say espresso
okay or else you can say coffee machine 200 ml of coffee and can you be a latte
this is syntax clear guys how you declare a function you pass a parameters and you execute
call that function this logic is clear right
when i'm calling this now let's say give me a second i'm not doing a console log here
let me make a console log because i'm not printing whatever is being returned from the function
now this particular string is returned right so i have to print that back
okay clear it and print it now do you see that i need 200 ml of espresso 200 ml of latte something
being printed now i can write this thing multiple times but what if this coffee machine is like
dynamic right whatever quantity you pass you'll get that item so that's where function should
be designed or used or created whenever you have a same logic and same task to be done again and
again i hope uh this particular data types are clear like if i have to show you type of also i'll
show this one type of a function uh coffee machine let's say uh i print this one i'm getting as a
function okay for all the other primitive non-primitive data types we got as an object
for this one we got as a function i'll tell you why we got this as a function also in future
but remember this one any doubts guys still know in data types file whatever we have typed
no doubts right now
this is the part that actually i wanted to teach you that's the content of it but i want to teach
you some more things like some methods on arrays because in future classes we might not have time
to deal with them instead of this can we use let and later const uh
this is a dynamic way or else you can use this way also let's say i can use
one of the ways writing this one very i'll talk about the syntax later const uh kabir let's say
uh how can i build this because these variables are already initialized and you are just you need
to consume that one of the ways like if you want to build a string and return it let's say
item uh and you can say this one directly let's say i need uh and you can say quantity
quantity all right you see you can say drink
and also you can return this item both both things will work
okay let's type it down you see this i'm also getting that but just to add more spaces right
let's say i'm having the space also i'm having more space what's that one line of okay
this is how also you can write you can also directly return it i hope this is clear
okay
going right guys uh few things on arrays right few things on arrays that i want to discuss
yeah using dynamic strings is a practice that's how you will be doing it but yes let's focus on
this let's say i have uh this list of elements till 10
okay now how can i know how many items are there in this array
what is the one thing that we can use like what is this particular how many items are there in
this array like length right uh let's say if i do console dot log a dot
length okay let's say this is a function uh i don't remember this is a function
okay i am not executing right file uh let's say ls cd dot dot ls
uh node arrays dot js okay it's not a function actually whenever you do this you'll be able to
print it okay directly whenever it's like a primitive value where it will be updated so if
you want to use uh know the size of it so size of an array you can use array dot length i hope this
property is clear guys length property
right now for i trading an array you have two ways okay one is a simple loop where i can you can do
this what i'm doing is like i'm i trading from its particular a zeroth index to its length and i'm
trying to print each index okay let's do this one i'm able to print it the other the other way
around is using map a dot map or let me not teach map as of now we'll go back to uh map again in
future uh what else i have to cover give me a second guys yeah map we can learn later
we'll go for forage example let's say now what does forage does is that it will pick item by item
it will pick item by item instead like sometimes yeah let's say
okay now here you are getting an access to a index level let's say you want to access by indexes
in arrays indexes always start from zero that is what we we know clearly when we have already
learned dsa now this both loops are working in same way i trading through from zeroth index to
last index but here you have an ability to select an index here it will you know do the like it will
run through the loop it will try to print each and every element let's say i try to do this
you see it is trying to print that same one to ten one to ten both the two times okay two ways
of i trading for loop i hope this thing is clear is uh how you can i treat an array
yes i treating an array is clear right when to use what okay now whenever you have you're dealing
with an index right let's say uh now if i want to print only even based index items or odd based
index items you would do this logic right you will do this one right console log off
you have in this use case only printing even items but you cannot write that logic here you don't know
simply but you always here also you have uh index let's say i write down this logic here
uh both the things can be used actually
let's say i comment this because this is clear for us anyways
a simple use case let's see if this is working see i'm able to still print
uh all the
hey okay index if i do i'm printing all the odd elements right
so index here starting is from i think it's starting from
from
give me a second if i print only index
so i'm getting all the index zero to nine that's fine i'm checking to i'm trying to print only even
indexes so this should be working fine right it should give me all the elements
or let's say you can get only index value here that will give you again
but generally the more handling like for each loop is going through whenever you want to do
some iteration let's say now each element you want to do some operation on it let's say return
or console do console dot log a common operation let's say element dot element multiplied by three
you want to do a common operation across them then you can use something like a for each loop
where you are trying to do for every item like for each item you are doing some some same logic
okay but whereas you need a more control over it then you have to go for this one
this one if you need a further more control then you can go for map i'll tell you
of which one to use when in the future once we introduce map i'll take all three of examples
but i'm just trying to teach you syntax check there are the two ways of iterating over the loop
is that point clear yes no then let's say now i want to add an item into this an array if i want
to add an item into this an array then you have something called as method called as push we just
do a push of 11 item if you do console log of a let's say i try to print a now
do you see this item 11 got added because we pushed an item into it now the push method adds
item into into the array at the last position
okay and let's say if i do something like a dot pop
console log of a now let's say if i'm doing this i am trying to re-execute it
now if you see first when i pushed an item and console log i am able to see one to 11 items
and when i'm when i try to print one to like i after pop i'm trying to print it again
you are able to see like oh that item 11 has been removed right
isn't it
here in the next take second example so what pop does it it removes an item from the last portion
okay and i think guys earlier also this was working fine when i was running through the index
reason i'll tell you let's say if i print this and i use this logic
let's say i use i here instead of index i declared it at this way
now let's say i call this as a function of the index and let's say i call this as a function of
index i declared it at this way now let's say i comment below things for a second
and i print it so if you see i'm printing uh three uh nine oh okay uh element into three so
i don't need to do this uh i'm print only element let's say clear this again i'm able to three
print one three five seven nine reason i'll tell you one three finance one because we started with
index one two three four always like the zeroth index is even index so it starts for one and then
it printed uh index two then index four right we are doing uh printing all even index item so we
are also having an index inside the for each i hope that point is clear right are also having
index in for each look also going back to this one i hope push and pop is also clear now here
uh one of the new tools methods are available in javascript if you want to play around with the
first element of an array add a new element of the first to the array it's like you know
to dq where you can in the queue you have a double like nq right sorry dq where you can add
and remove from the first and last both places right it works in the same way here like if you
want to let's say i do something called a dot shift okay and i try to console log now let's
say what is the output what happened guys i pushed an 11 item 11 and i console log one to 11 are
there then i popped an item so 11th item was removed when i popped it and it did something
called a shift now when i shifted the first item got removed so whenever you use shift method it
means that it is it will remove an item from the start i hope that point is clear shift is used to
remove items from start of an array
okay if you want to add an item into the start right let's say i go and do something like unshift
unshift and add okay this will help us
to add an item onto the start again let's say i clear this console for us
okay if you see we removed item one then we did unshift of one it added item one onto the first
is this clear guys shift unshift
okay
i hope this all the methods whatever we discussed are clear
then there is some one method called as slice
let's say i use something called as a dot slice
slice is used to you know like works like a
knife generally what it does is like whenever you say that whenever you cut let's say you have a
banana you slice the banana what it does once you do a slice what it does it is broken into two parts
right and you get the one part and you give the other person the other part if you are slicing it
right so it works in the same way slice is actually dividing an array into two pieces
now if i say slice when i'm making a slice i have to decide the position where i want to make a
slice of it so if i did if i let's say that i am making a slice of position three when i'm giving
a three i mean to say that i'm giving an index three and what is slice doesn't slice gives back as
an array after being sliced now when it is being sliced right let's say this is a banana
you sliced it in between let's say in middle element middle index the first half of the
banana you will get it back returned in the b item okay let's say i try to do console log of b
i'll show you here with an example let's say i comment this thing
okay clear
do you see uh sorry guys you return you actually get last items i mean to say starting from that
index like first like if you go by writing an index right zero one two and three when you slice
this item you got actually all the remaining items is that clear like slice is actually dividing an
array into two pieces given a starting index you you have to that will be returning you you
cannot use that immediately but you have to store it in a new variable to slice it okay
um divides an array into two pieces
and returns other half as new array
okay other half
that's new array okay because why i'm saying is a new array is like let's say
i try to print a here now let's see what's there in a
do you see the one array is not disturbed only uh like whatever copy you are getting in b
that will be there like you can get the items that you want and store it here
okay item a will be still uh persist tejal
i'll show you like if you want only item let's say
con see a dot slice let's say i give zero comma three
okay when you do this console dot log of c you will get the initial items
if you see here so it takes either of index start index and index if you are giving only
one index it will consider as a end index yeah it's like a substring but it works on array
cool so you can say uh start and end index
whatever you want to give the whenever whenever you are giving three
and you're not defining the last index by default it will consider the length of that array
okay which is a dot length minus one this is something we know right by default but
it's given by default okay uh is slice clear guys
okay i hope uh no one else is having doubts on this then i'll give you one uh homework guys
to understand it one method called as splice i'll take this in the first uh point when we start the
class i'll tell it what it does it is helped to it it is helpful to add items remove items
and replace items in an array
this one particular method can be helpful to do all the operations splice is that powerful
it's a combination of adding removing and replacing okay you guys just explore this one
and we'll come back in the next class and i'll try to help you out understand this
okay with few more i'll i'll try to enlarge more uh you know uh with more amount of examples then
we'll explore this there are few more methods like you know uh because uh there are methods like map
okay reduce filter all this like methods are there on array which are like bit advanced
i'll take one by one with the concept these are the initial set of methods that you might be
dealing with manipulating an array or i treating to an array okay we'll pick them in future but
these are the usual uh arrays like whatever methods that you see in daily life but the
other advanced methods that you come across we'll explore that in future i hope that point is clear
guys so guys uh i hope you guys enjoyed this video and i hope you guys enjoyed this video
so guys uh are there any doubts are there any doubts in today's class if you have doubts please
stay in call or else uh the content for today's class is over i hope you like liked it uh enjoyed
it with history of js and getting started with js part and uh meet you soon in the next class
on tuesday but one thing i want to say you guys is that prepare well and give your best attempt
in the context or whatever html css we have learned revise it complete your assignments
and let's come back okay but uh okay vignesh i'll try to revise what slice does okay firstly slice
divides array into two pieces okay and it returns let's say returns and as a new array
okay okay now so a slice generally takes two things
starting index
and ending index
like from where to where you need an array because it it is returning we have to tell like when we
are storing inside a variable from where to where you need it if you are giving only one variable
it means it will consider that is as a starting index and by default if you're not giving an
ending index it will consider ending index as a last element of this array that's the reason why
we were able to get from starting from index third till the last item of 10
when when i did this so how does it work like even if i give
a dot length minus one it is still same even if i don't declare it here by implicitly it
will take that one as an end of array but if you want a specific uh you know range of elements in
your new array that you're creating you can give starting index and end index okay now guys i have
one topic actually that you know one question actually in assignments that was asked
okay that i have to take it i forgot it i hope no one got dropped off the call right i can pick it up
let's say i'll create a new file new folder
css doubts
i'll keep keep as css doubts for us so that if if anytime we are
uh not exactly that one but uh i think some bit you yourself you yourself reached it right
z index and what was the other one
index and what was the other one
what was the other one what is that like who raised it guys in the initial class
margin collapse right yeah akabey thank you so uh give me a second i'll pull an example
so
okay let's say i have a diff and i have a paragraph tag in that i see lorem 20
okay and i try to recreate this one
so
and i go into style block
uh i'll talk to the talk to about large ungeth
okay i use div tag then
uh i what i'll do is like i'll add something called as margin let's say first we give uh border
of two pixel solid black and let's say i have some padding of 10 pixel
and i'll keep margin as a 10 pixel on each side there's nothing new i have done right kabir
till now where it comes to uh things that we have discussed let me open with this one as a live server
so
now if you see here one thing firstly i'll go into the body tag i'll open the diff now for diff i've
declared margin for top bottom left right as 10 pixel is that clear now when i have two diffs
for this one margin bottom would be 10 pixel for this one margin top would be 10 pixel right
like first day when second day just
are you able to follow uh guys everyone like first day when second day first day margin bottom will
be 10 pixel and for second day margin top will be 10 pixel so combined height of both margin should
be 20 pixel isn't it the gap between here should be 20 pixel right but here if you go and see
if you go and see what it is 10 pixel if i go and hit here it's still 10 pixel
why that is happening so what it will does is it will take it will collapse the margin it will
combine like let's say there are now i have took an example of 10 10 pixel okay just it should be
20 but it worked as a 10 reason i'll tell you whenever you have two elements working right
uh again when i explained your box model what we thought of margin as a distance between two houses
isn't it
let's say this is a house one this is a house too if i say this house should be 10 pixel away from
the left house this house will say that i should be 10 pixel away from the right house it doesn't
mean that both should be away of 20 pixel when i add it if they maintain 10 pixel of gap that
is enough isn't it that is what margin collapse happens margin collapse is a phenomenon
which will take like a maximum amount let's say this says that but this example is clear let's
take something else what i'll do is that i'll give an id here as first item
i'll give id as second item
okay now let's say this is hashtag first item
i'll say copy this one and i say
second item and i'll give something margin as 12 pixel
okay now let's see what happened if i go over here and i select the pixel okay let's say i
let's say i select for first item first okay here still the margin is 10 pixel only
okay but there is a space between below right if you see there is a some space if i try to zoom it
in i'm not able to zoom in this one if i hover this item top item there is a space a slight
space right that two pixel extra that is coming from below stop margin margin top because here
this item is having 12 so whenever there is a house right or whenever there is a something
diff margin collapse will always take maximum of two items margin
as margin okay let's say as margin
so are you able to understand margin collapse property guys
yeah it's a default behavior open
okay uh i'll just check kabir has given me thumbs up yeah great now then
then there was another question that kabir has asked me is like about
uh like absolute uh like this one z index now let's say i make both the positions as absolute
guys help me out what will happen if i make both the positions as absolute
what should be the behavior we have learned this one you should know it
and i'll give something background color as red and blue
yes what should happen
whenever position absolute is applied let's go back to this one
top right window right both will move to top right window with respect to top
top right window parent related if here we don't have parent related if so everything both should
be aligned to the top left right if you see both are aligned to top left firstly because the content
is more if i reduce the content let's say if i reduce the content as uh lorem five four okay
lorem four uh
okay now they are both are aligned to top left but do you see here blue is coming on top of
this item first item is that point clear like both are moved both are having color different
color one is having red one is having blue now what if i want red to come on top what if i want
on top what if i want red to come on top then i can do something called as z index
and i can say two
what does it mean whenever z index is a property that can be applied only to something like
position absolute or multi-layered and this multi-layer can happen only when i say this layers
example right if you see here does this portion create layers when applied if you see these
examples relative fixed sticky and absolute whenever this layering is happening if you want
a particular box to be top off on something or behind something you can play around with this
property called as z index what if i want now blue item to come on the top z index value of red
is two and i'll go here i'll say z index of this item make it three so whatever z index will have
no not exactly an absolute kabir i'm saying that whichever is creating multi-layers right
sticky absolute anything you apply z index value is generally like whichever is creating multi-layer
okay multi-layer for them you can use z index which one should come on which on top of it
so you can generally is used to show which will override the other one behind the scenes
i hope z index is also clear guys what does that index do
okay great guys so yeah this was the two doubts kabir has asked me so i hope these are also
resolved one thing i'll do is i'll push the code and i'll push the other things like content that
you can refer to and other things later class eight notes welcome class eight notes
welcome kabir so
yeah you can say that something let's say if i say if i show you right z index property
okay if you see they use an example of absolute like they say that z index property specifies
the stack of order of element now the stack becomes only when you have multi-layered
okay now they said z index only work on a position element absolute relative
fixed and sticky right that's when you create multi-layer right two three layers of items
yeah yeah that's how works okay they also say that flex items that are directly children of
flex items because using flex right you you you some people specifically play around with items
right position of items in grid you you can see like you explore from grid row one by three grid
column two by three or you extend it now if both things are colliding how can you manage it so
those sort of properties but z index is generally used when you have multi-layer structure that
concept should be clear
okay so other than this one i had some bit question
let me go back and check this guys i'll start the doubt session for our sake before i start
taking any other things so anyone having any doubts they can stay guys in the call or else
free free free free to drop the call saturday we don't have class please attempt your contest
and do well guys i would be waiting for your feedback like how was the contest and how how
you're able to do it do let me know if you face any challenges do let me know drop in whatsapp chat
okay well i'll help you out if you need anything from my side so this seems to be a react project
okay grid layout
uh this is a base file home page.js you have nav header slides and footer and then you have
okay you you didn't anything print as a new layout
okay fine home page then you went to homepage.css then applied a grid properties into it
and this property is some bit yeah i'll do this one unmute you
yeah some bit uh try to speak i want to mute you yeah i'm audible yes yes yeah so like my question
is if you like run this js file right do npm start or something let's say i clone clone your website
let's say i clone clone your website
this js file even though it has the same css right it doesn't cover the whole page but the
same css file if you can go to that layout.html file which is in new layout or some file it covers
the whole page that's the doubt why there's a difference okay i will check that
version
bbill plugin version
then i have issue with the installation of this one like i was also getting that same issue but
it was running in my system it was just showing it as a warning okay uh let's do one thing clean
this one npm cache clean hyphen hyphen force
then npm i
the existing package dot lock dot json file right that's what creating an issue
but you can delete that file and clean the cache like i tried to add a dependency in that okay
but again there was some version
you used create react app no yeah this one
white is also good but we'll use react create react app itself for learning react but that's
easy because it's that's been legacy how it works
how it works
let's wait for a minute till it install but uh like then app.css
it doesn't cover whole thing you know you can go to view change or something that above file
view change yeah you can do this show preview thing uh okay that's fine uh okay this is not
working uh for me this is fine this is something example we have already learned tensors that's
fine correct so this thing has the same css okay in that home page dot css okay this is a js file
but for this i have to run the react app right uh let's do one thing what i'll do
is like can i create a new project itself here uh let's say i
have a test app
test app
I guess it's NPX, sorry, note package executor, what I believe is that, where you might have
messed up, so there are two things, if you see, what is a root file, app.js, if you go
and see here, in app.js, there are some default styles, you wouldn't clean it up, those are
applied directly on an app file, and second thing that you might have messed up is that
one, this on the index.css, if you see, on body, margin is fine, but padding and everything
should be cleaned up, I'm assuming that root files have not been cleaned up, but if there
are any other issues, right, I'll explore that, yeah, like what's happening is it's only covering
the whole three columns, right, they're only covering one third of the page, okay, that,
we can explore that issue, not a big deal, let's say I copy our, this one, app.js, let's
say, copy this, then I'll try to replicate your issue, firstly, home page, let's say
I copy this file, and I paste it in the src, and I also copy this one, I paste it in here,
okay, I minimize this one, and I go to package.json, then I start command run, okay, I have another
app running, why, starting development server 302, let's say I have this site, so if you
see this, firstly, it's covering one by third, right, one thing you can always do is, like
you can go and see, what are the other things, if you see by default, grid is applied, so
grid is applied, and first column is only coming for 20%, okay, if I edit this one,
and I make one fr, let's say directly, one fr, okay, this will work by default, but where
coming, that we have to figure it out, right, if I explore this, div root, on this thing,
we don't have the grid, on the body level, I'm having, okay, I agree, this grid is coming
here in the body tag, if you go and see, firstly, index.js, css, on the body, we have applied
some of the things, let's say, in app.js, we can remove that import, I guess, that import,
right, I can say directly padding, zero, margin zero, okay, now, if I refresh the app, no,
I need to restart it, it compiled, is it compiled, npmbram start, okay, let's say, I go to package.json,
again, I still execute this file, why, okay, still, I'm able to see the grid, okay, yeah,
let's go back and see why this is happening, what if I remove this, this is fine, as soon as I gave
this, height is 100 vh, now, let's make width, yeah, if I increase the width, it's working, like,
it is taking 100 view, okay, so, by default, we are assuming that width is not being consumed
completely, you know, yeah, so, let's do this one, why it is not consuming whole width, firstly,
and if I remove this property, one thing, it's, if you see grid, right, grid, whatever grid areas
you used, okay, that thing is being applied, because if you see the sections, right, side
section is coming here, content section is here, those sections are divided right away, footer
section here, but all things are assumed to be in this one, correct, so, it's coming inside the 20
pixel, now, if I go in the header section, now, what is being applied here, it's the same example,
though, but where did it messed up, let's explore this one, yeah, there is some issue in the template
areas, huh, so, let's explore this one, firstly, header is grid area, header section, fine,
but here, if I go and check in the, this one, the way grid template areas, we have defined it,
header section, header section, header section, this is fine, supposed to consume whole thing,
okay, by default, it is consuming,
because, one thing, if I remove this width, let's say, I make three columns, I don't give FR unit,
okay, 20%, and I say 20%, let's see, this is working, no, no, I have tried every, like,
thing, 44, other units, other units you have tried, yes, yes, only the, every change that we make on
the first one, right, only that is getting affected, the rest two are, okay, because,
what I assumed, right, firstly, the value by default, whatever you have applied,
it was having FR unit, if you don't provide width, how this FR will be calculated is something that
I'm assuming, okay, I was thinking, like, with respect to the window size, it's calculating
something like that, okay, if we consider that way, let's say, if I select this item,
let's say, I'm not able to select this content area itself,
because everything is dissolving here itself, but,
yeah, I think it's about something that,
like, let's say, is it, is it necessary to provide
width of container while using grid?
Okay, I'm trying to learn, yes, I know,
yeah, they have provided a width of 100%, right, so, I believe we need to provide width,
why not write a simple code, but,
and also, I guess, HTML provides some default width, because it was written, like, when we,
if we can go to the file, right, okay, which file, any HTML file, by default, any default
HTML file, right, yeah, let's say, this is an index, index.html, and I think you can do, yeah,
like, width is equal to device width or something,
yeah, if I, if I use this meta tag, then, if I use this meta tag, let's say, in this app itself,
let's go, yeah, I guess, then it might work, it might work, but let's explore this index,
this is a JS file, where is the HTML public folder, HTML, and either with device width, yeah,
yeah, so, this is not coming from there, okay, I'll explore the reasoning and I'll get back to you,
but, I think, width is something we have to provide, but, I am not exactly sure whether
it is mandatory, Sambit, I'll come back and let you know on that, yeah, sure, I'll also try to
see now, yes, well, this is really corner case, like, generally, like, firstly,
whenever you are using fractional unit, how does fractional unit is calculated, that we have to
specifically tell, that is what my belief is, but, if you are not, let's say, if I don't keep height
also, do you see, it also broke the height part, yeah, so, I believe this height and width is
something that needed to be provided, and by default, for index, that simple file, right,
while we are rendering, in your example, right, in your app, where you use this one,
let's explore this one, if I open this on a live server, okay, this file, right,
let's say, I go and open a grid layout, I have height, if I remove this height also, if you see,
it's breaking in a way, yeah, okay, but, how does width is calculated as 100%, you know,
if I go for the computed, always go for the computed, if you want to calculate what is
the height and width of it, I got height, then, let's say, I go for width, if you see,
by default, I'm able to get it, but, for our app, if I go in the app, if I select for the body tag,
and I go for computed, width I'm getting as 1433, but, if I go for the, this root element,
this is the body, right, I go and select here, my width is coming as 286, do you see this, yeah,
correct, there's a difference between what our content is being consumed, and what our
screen is providing, yeah, so, wherever, I believe, wherever you are using a grid, right,
it is supposed to, you give that how much percentage of screen I need, then, it will be fixed,
yeah, got it, yeah, it's better to always give the
that's how, I mean, behind the scenes, how, because, I'll tell you, now, inside the react,
right, this thing that you are building, returning back that, this each and every step, if you see,
default folder, it is creating a, inside using react-dom, it is creating a new element, right,
root element, that is acting as a base file, now, how they are appending, how they are distributing
is something we don't exactly know, so, it is assumed to be, take full content, and play around
with that, yeah, it might be different in case of html, and this thing, right, yeah, good, good one,
you tried on react, that's good, okay, yeah, I hope your doubt is solved, up to an extent, right,
yeah, yeah, yeah, I'm clear, sure, thank you, so, I'm muting, yeah, thanks a lot, yeah, sure,
guys, any other doubts, if you have any other doubts, or any other one, who tried this use
cases, let me delete this, thank you, Maneshwara, Ankit, if Ankit is there, Ankit is there,
Ankit, you are facing challenge in understanding JS, or how, what was your opinion on that,
I just seen your comment, I was not able to respond to that, but I just want to understand like,
it's hard for you, so, one thing, one thing I would say is that, whenever you feel this one right,
something that I don't understand, right, one time, what we are supposed to do, we are going,
we are supposed to go and understand, repeat it, right, or else go to github repo, and just see
those syntaxes, but if you are facing any challenge, understanding that concept,
talk to me in the class itself, directly, I'll try to repeat that content, I'll try to do best
for myself, if it's something new, you are trying to learn, it is supposed to be difficult, and
let's try to put best efforts from our side, and let's see, if it is still not working out,
we'll figure it out, okay, yeah, it's something new, I would definitely say that, it's difficult
to verify, understand, or even if you understand it, that needs some practice to come with,
okay, so, let's keep spending some time at the end of the journey, right, just try to give your
best efforts from this Jan 18 to Feb month, all the concepts, I, hopefully, I'll drive you to the
best of knowledge, and I hope you will be confident with this language, okay, because today,
it was really simple, basic variables and data types, just go through it, revise the content,
any challenge, bring me directly, I'll try to help you out, okay,
so, hello guys, then, if that is solved,
I'll close the session for today, see you on Tuesday, guys,
yeah, yeah, I'm there on WhatsApp group, I'm there, okay,
okay, great, no worries,
yeah, good night, Ankit, good night, all, good night, all, take care,
see you on Tuesday, hope you do your assignment and have fun on this weekend,
or complete assignments and then have fun, that is what I would say, so, hello, guys, bye-bye,